Alice Corona

Data-Driven Storyteller · Consultant · Trainer · Researcher

I AM A RESEARCHER SPECIALIZED IN DATA-DRIVEN METHODOLOGIES FOR STORYTELLING.

I have years of experience working as a **data journalist** and I've counseled NGOs, non-profits and businesses on producing data-driven stories. I've given **talks, trainings and workshops** on data-driven storytelling techniques. I was lead data journalist and trainer at <u>Silk.co</u>, a semantic web platform for publishing and visualizing data. I privilege the use of **open source tools and/or of coding**.

SKILLS

Research	Using multiple methodologies (content analysis of texts & digital entities; research interview; survey; frame analysis); finding data for stories & how to access it & how to complement it
Data scraping	Getting the data in a machine-readable format. Python, APIs, XPath scraping in Google Sheets
Data wrangling	Cleaning and restructuring of messy data. OpenRefine + GREL expressions, Python, RegEx
Data analysis	Exploratory + statistical analysis. Google Sheets/Excel, Python
Data storytelling	Putting together insights to form a story; presenting the story; finding possible gaps and limitations
Data visualization	Networks visualizations, maps, timelines, (interactive) charts, infographics

WORK EXPERIENCE

Data-Driven Storytelling Consultant & Researcher

Aug. 2016 - Present

@ Freelancer

- Assisting clients (NGOs, academia and journalists) with data driven stories/research
- Trainer at international and local events (see events section of my website for list)

Lead Data Journalist & Trainer

Jan. 2014 - Aug. 2016

@ Silk.co

The startup behind the semantic platform for data publishing and interactive storytelling. Successfully acquired by Palantir in Aug. 2016.

- Hired to boost Silk's content marketing strategy.
- Creator of viral stories that generate traffic and visibility on social media and international news outlets.
- Projects featured in The Guardian, Information is Beautiful, Vox, CNN, The Atlantic and others
- Trainer at international and local events (see <u>events</u> section of my website for list))

Research Assistant

Sept. 2013 - Jan. 2014

@ DataJLab

A virtual lab at Tilburg University on data journalism trends and techniques

- Member of the "Climate Finance Lab" team, investigating financial data stories behind climate policies.
- Co-authored paper with Dr. Stefania Milan on journalism & algorithms. Selected for a panel at "Rethinking Journalism"

Journalist

May 2013 - Jan. 2014

@ Freelancer

• Published data-driven pieces for print and digital Italian outlets. Clients include Wired Italy and datajournalism.it

Journalist Trainee

April 2013 - June 2013

@ NRC next

Major Dutch newspaper.

• Internship that led to data-driven investigative journalism piece on Interpol

EDUCATION

Post-Graduate Learning

- Winter University: Using European data for better storytelling by European People's Party · Brussels, Belgium
- Shift, Shape, Mobilize Workshop by Sourcefabric and n-ost · Odessa, Ukraine
- Won scholarship for the Summer School for Journalists and Media Practitioners @ European University Institute · Fiesole, Italy
- Data4Change by SmallMedia and VisualizingImpact· Beirut, Lebanon
- Young European Journalist Workshop "Data and Journalism: Between big stories and dirty surveillance" · Potsdam, Germany
- Data Journalism Workshop "<u>Turning Data into Stories</u>" by MediaLab Prado · Madrid, Spain
- School of Data Journalism, workshops by School of Data · Perugia, Italy
- See the "Events" section of my website for others

Communication and Information Sciences (MA) · Data Journalism Track

August 2012 - August 2013

@University of Tilburg (The Netherlands)

- Graduated with distinction
- Thesis "Social meets civic: Civic social media and open government data: An inquiry on collaborative fact-checking for citizens' empowerment"
- One of the two students chosen for a data journalism internship at NRC Next (major Dutch newspaper)

History, Tradition and Innovation (BA)

September 2008 - July 2012

@University of Siena (Italy)

- Graduated cum laude
- Thesis analyzing media discourse in Italian newspapers during the 2011 was in Libya and NATO's
- Specialized in the period from the 1789 French Revolution to current days. Elective courses in Philosophy, Human Rights, Economic History and Globalization

MORE IN DEPHT

- You can view a portfolio of my projects at alice-corona.nl/portfolio
- You can read a list of training and workshops I've given, and see the slideshows of some, at alice-corona.nl/events
- You can have a look at a few tutorials I've written up at alice-corona.nl/tutorials

GET IN TOUCH

alice-corona.nl

8.a.c.huxl@gmail.com

+31 6 333 56867

FOLLOW



medium.com/@alice corona



twitter.com/alice_corona



github.com/ali-ce